<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
  Copyright 2017 Goldman Sachs.
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
  -->

<chapter >
    <title>Preface</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            The goal of this book is to introduce you to object-relational mapping using Reladomo.
            It provides a broad overview of various Reladomo features. The goal is to provide a feel and flavor for what is possible with Reladomo.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Audience</title>
        <para>
            This book is written for Java programmers who want to use Reladomo for object-relational mapping.
            This book assumes that the reader is familiar with the basic concepts behind object-relational mapping (such as domain modeling) and SQL.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>How to read this book</title>
        <para>
            This book is intentionally light on commentary and heavy on Java code examples and snippets. The reader is encouraged to consult and run the complete
            examples, which are distributed with this book.
        </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Examples</title>
            <para>
                The examples are structured as multiple Maven modules. These modules are referenced in
                various chapters in the book.
            </para>
            <para>
                To run the examples :
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Clone <code>https://github.com/goldmansachs/reladomo-kata</code>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Import the top level <code>reladomo-tour</code> as a Maven module
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Explore and run the main classes and tests in the various child Maven modules.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Conventions</title>
        <para>The following conventions have been used:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Example references - When a program/example listing refers to a source file, the title
                    of the listing is formatted as <code>&lt;name of maven module&gt;/&lt;name source file&gt;</code>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Elided examples - Elided examples contain the text <code>// elided for brevity</code>. For the full example,
                        consult the source file as indicated by the example's title.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Additional Documentation</title>
        <para>
            This book is meant to be a practical guide. It is not reference documentation. Documentation that explores various Reladomo features in more detailcan be found at the <emphasis><ulink url="https://github.com/goldmansachs/reladomo">Reladomo Github project page</ulink></emphasis>. Some of these documents
            have also been linked in various chapters in this book.
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
